Curriculum Vitae

PERSONAL INFORMATION





COMSATS University Islamabad Wah Campus, Wah Cantt 47040 Punjab Pakistan

Marital Status | Single Sex | Male Date of birth | 13/04/1994 Passport No: SF1333371

Objective:

A challenging position or research opportunity that will allow me to utilize my innovative problem solving skills and technical skills as well as experience for career growth in the field of Electrical Engineering, Renewable Energy and Sensor and Intelligent Instrument Technology.

Research Interests

Smart Grid, Demand Side Management, Optimization Techniques, Renewable Energy, Efficient and Clean Energy Utilization, Power System Operation and Control and Sensor and Intelligent Instrument Technology

EDUCATION BACKGROUND

September 2016 - May 2018

MS Electrical Engineering, major in Electrical Power

(CGPA: 3.65/4.00)

COMSATS University Islamabad Wah Campus, Wah Cantt 47040 Punjab Pakistan

Thesis: Energy Management Model for Smart Homes

Major Courses: (Smart Grid System Operation, Advance Power System Protection, Power Generation & Plant Operation, Renewable Energy Technologies, Optimization Techniques, Modeling and Simulation, Wireless Network and Wireless Sensor Networks)

October 2012 – July 2016 BSc Electrical Engineering, major in Electrical Power

(CGPA: 3.53/4.00)

Wah Engineering College, University of Wah, Quaid Avenue Road, Wah Cantt Punjab Pakistan.

Dissertation: Intelligent Traffic and Smart Lighting Control System

Major Courses: (Power Generation, Power Distribution & Utilization, Power Transmission,

Renewable Energy System and Power System Analysis)

Higher Secondary School Certificate (F.Sc)

(GRADE: A)

June 2009 - May 2012

BISE Multan 60000, Punjab Pakistan.

Pre-Engineering (Physics, Chemistry, Mathematics)
 Secondary School Certificate (Matric)

(GRADE: A)

April 2007 – August 2009

Govt. Public high school Dokota, BISE Multan 60000, Punjab Pakistan.

Science (Physics, Chemistry, Biology, Mathematics)

WORKING EXPERIENCES

March 2018 - Present

Graduate Research Assistant

COMSATS University Islamabad Wah Campus, Wah Cantt 47040 Punjab Pakistan

HEC-SRGP Project Title: "Distributed Congestion-aware Traffic Load Balancing through Routing in

Low Power and Limited Broadcast Range Wireless Ad Hoc Networks".

January 2017 – June 2018

Resident Supervisor

Shahid & Co (PVT) Ltd, Rawat Islamabad Pakistan

July 2015 - August 2015

Internee Engineer

Internee Engineer

Pakistan Aeronautical Complex (PAC) Kamra, Punjab Pakistan

July 2014 - August 2014

Multan Electric Power Company (MEPCO) Multan, Punjab Pakistan

PERSONAL SKILLS

Language(s)

Punjabi (Mother Tongue), Urdu (Native) , English (Conversational) English

UNDERSTANDING		SPEAKING		WRITING
Listening	Reading	Spoken interaction	Spoken production	
EXCELLENT	VERY GOOD	GOOD	GOOD	VERY GOOD

Communication Skills Managerial and Leadership Skills Good communications skills, both written and oral and motivating skills.

- Time management, project management, ability to meet deadlines
- Teamwork and group participation
- Good interpersonal and analytical skills

Curriculum Vitae

Research and Presentation Skills

- Research in the area background smart grid, optimization techniques and Low Power wireless Ad Hoc Networks.
- Prepares literature reviews and analyses data.
- Presented data clearly and confidently to both small and large groups.
- Wrote scientific articles in international conferences and journals, as well as the highly technical replies to the questions raised by the reviewers.
- Coached and collaborated with other scientists, outlining objectives, methodology, and conclusions, actively listening to people and stimulating interest and discussion.
- Produced regular progression reports.

Computer and Technical Skills

- Electrical Projects & Maintenance: Good understanding of Electrical Drawings, Planning of Projects, Erection & Maintenance. Both practical as well as theoretical knowledge of Different Electrical Instruments. Working more efficiently so that maximum output comes.
- Circuits and Simulation Software (PSPICE, Live Wire, Proteus, COMSOL Multiphysics and Power world Simulator)
- Good command of MATLAB (SIM Power System, Signal Processing,)
- Programming and Designing Software (C++, Turbo C, AutoCAD, LaTeX and Adobe Photoshop)
- Web Development: PHP, HTML, Java Script, JQUERY, CSS and WordPress.
- Operating Systems: Windows XP/7/8/8.1/10.
- Proficiency in Microsoft Office (Word, Power Point and Excel).

PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS

- Registered Engineer Pakistan Engineering Council (PEC), Pakistan. (Life Time Member)
- Member of Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE) Society
- Member of Industrial visit committee at Shahid & Co (PVT) Ltd, Islamabad Pakistan

FREELANCING CAREER

February 2016 - Present

Freelancing Skills

Web Developer, SEO Expert and Social Media Manager

- Developing and maintaining the front end functionality of websites.
- Participating in discussions with clients to clarify what they want.
- Designing prototypes for apps and websites.
- Creating logos, banners and buttons for websites.
- Providing technical support to end users.
- Identifying and correcting software deficiencies.
- Devising SEO strategies based around specific keywords
- Involved in creating a comparison site from scratch.
- Participated in brainstorming sessions to come up with ideas.
- Documented software and technical specifications.
- Provided guidance and advice to less experienced staff.
- Worked on multiple projects simultaneously to a high standard.
- Escalated operational issues to senior management.
- Involved in a project to develop a large online gaming website.
- Addressed cross-browser compatibility issues.
- Integrated websites with Facebook, Twitter, and YouTube.

Techniques

- Search Engine Optimization (SEO)
- Social Media Marketing (SMM)
- Social Engine Marketing (SEM)
- Digital Marketing & Advertising
- Social Media Optimization
- Digital Branding
- SEO Writing

AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS

Appointed as the Group leader of final year project by University during B.Sc. Studies.

- Awarded fifty percent merit scholarship for B.Sc. Electrical (Power) Engineering in University of Wah, Wah Cantt Punjab Pakistan.
- Secured 1st position in 2nd and 3rd Semesters Exam of B.Sc. Electrical (Power) Engineering.
- Awarded Merit scholarship for MS Electrical (Power) Engineering in COMSATS University Islamabad Wah Campus, Wah Cantt Punjab Pakistan.
- Awarded Certificate of Completion (Freelancing Training in Technical Domain) by Punjab Information Technology Board.

EXTRA CO-CURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

- Participated in "13th International Conference on Frontiers of Information Technology (FIT-2017)", Dec 2017, Serena Hotel, Islamabad.
- Participant of CPD on Game Theory for Wireless Systems (CUI Wah Campus)
- Participant of CPD workshop on Technology Awareness & Virtualization (CUI Wah Campus)
- Participant of Air Tech-16 (Air University)
- Participant of Talent Expo (Islamabad Pakistan)
- Participant of Second Multi-Disciplinary Student Research Conference (University of Wah)
- Participant of CPD workshop on Arduino Controller (Wah Engineering College)
- Participant of CPD on Graphene (Wah Engineering College)
- Participant of IEEE WEC Chapter on 3D Printing and Speed Wiring
- A willingness to travel, Reading Technology related Articles, Playing Snooker.

PUBLICATIONS

Conferences:

- [1] **M. Nadeem iqbal**, Sajid Saleem, Sajid IRan Khan, Wahab Ali, Usman Khalid and Mazhar Iqbal, "Intelligent Traffic and Smart Lighting Control System ", MDSRC 2016 Proceedings, 16-17 November, 2016 Wah Cantt Punjab, Pakistan, 2016. (pp. 54-61).
- [2] Khalid, Muhammad Usman, Nadeem Javaid, **Muhammad Nadeem Iqbal**, Aqib Jamil, Naveed Anwar, and Qazi Muhammad Fazal E. Haq. "Hybrid Bacterial Foraging Tabu Search Energy Optimization Technique in Smart Homes." In *Conference on Complex, Intelligent, and Software Intensive Systems*, pp. 25-36. Springer, Cham, 2018.
- [3] Khalid, Muhammad Usman, Nadeem Javaid, **Muhammad Nadeem Iqbal**, Ali Abdur Rehman, Muhammad Umair Khalid, and Mian Ahmer Sarwar. "Cooperative Energy Management Using Coalitional Game Theory for Reducing Power Losses in Microgrids." In *Conference on Complex, Intelligent, and Software Intensive Systems*, pp. 317-328. Springer, Cham, 2018.
- [4] Fatima, Itrat, Nadeem Javaid, **Muhammad Nadeem Iqbal**, Isra Shafi, Ayesha Anjum, and Ubed Memon. "Integration of cloud and fog based environment for effective resource distribution in smart buildings." In *14th IEEE International Wireless Communications and Mobile Computing Conference (IWCMC-2018)*, pp. 2-6. 2018.
- [5] Rahim, Muhammad Hassan, Nadeem Javaid, **Muhammad Nadeem Iqbal**, Sundas Shafiq, Muhammad Umair Khalid, and Ubed Ullah Memon. "Exploiting heuristic techniques for efficient energy management system in smart grid." In *14th IEEE International Wireless Communications and Mobile Computing Conference (IWCMC-2018)*, pp. 18-26. 2018.

Proceedings (Conferences):

- [1] Rehman, Malik Hassan Abdul, Nadeem Javaid, **Muhammad Nadeem Iqbal**, Zaheer Abbas, Muhammad Awais, Ahmed Jaffar Khan, and Umar Qasim. "Demand Side Management Using Hybrid Genetic Algorithm and Pigeon Inspired Optimization Techniques." The 32-nd IEEE International Conference on Advanced Information Networking and Applications (#1570420483 Accepted).
- [2] Asif Khan, Nadeem Javaid, **Muhammad Nadeem Iqbal**, Naveed Anwar, Inzimam ul Haq and Faraz Ahmad, "Time and device based priority induced demand side load management in smart home with consumer budget limit" The 32-nd IEEE International Conference on Advanced Information Networking and Applications, (#1570420530 Accepted). [3] Aqib Jamil, Nadeem Javaid, Muhammad Khalid, **Muhammad Nadeem Iqbal**, Saad
- Rashid and Naveed Anwar "An Energy Efficient Scheduling of a Smart Home Based on Optimization Techniques", The 12-th International Conference on Innovative Mobile and Internet Services in Ubiquitous Computing (IMIS-2018). (#1570419931 Accepted).

Curriculum Vitae

First name (Muhammad Nadeem) Surname (Iqbal)

[4] Rasool Bukhsh, Nadeem Javaid, Zafar Iqbal, Usman Ahmed, Zeeshan Ahmed and **Muhammad Nadeem Iqbal**, "Appliances Scheduling using Elephant Herd Optimization and Hybrid EHO for Residential Demand Response Using Multiple OTIs", The 32-nd IEEE International Conference on Advanced Information Networking and Applications, (#1570416406 Accepted).

REFERENCES

• Engr. Dr. Nadia Nawaz Qadri (Chairperson)

Department of Electrical Engineering, Comsats University Islamabad, Wah Campus, Wah Cantt. Pakistan.

Cell: +92(0)519272615

Email: drnadia@ciitwah.edu.pk

Dr. Omer Chughtai (Assistant Professor)

Department of Electrical Engineering, Comsats University Islamabad, Wah Campus, Wah Cantt. Pakistan.

Cell: +92(0) 519272247

Email: umer@ciitwah.edu.pk

Mr. Haris Masood (Assistant Professor)

Department of Electrical Engineering, Wah Engineering College Wah Cantt, Pakistan.